[MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: So in this
video, we're going
to talk about how to dynamically
allocate memory in C.
Now, as a disclaimer, if you haven't
watched our video on pointers
or aren't generally familiar
with the concept of pointers,
you're probably going to want to
take a look at that before this.
This video, dynamic memory
allocation in general,
works specifically with pointers.
So you're going want to
make sure that you're
comfortable with that before
diving in to this particular video.
Without further ado, let's get started.
Now, we've already seen how
to work with pointers before.
But typically, we've only
done it in the context
of pointing a pointer variable
that we declare statically
at another variable that already exists.
You may recall from
our video on pointers,
we had a line like int x equals 5.
And then we would say int
star px equals ampersand x.
But that's the only way we've
seen how to work with pointers.
And that's static
pointer usage, basically.
In order to work with pointers
statically as we have,
we need to know exactly
how much memory we're
going to use at the moment
we compile our program.
So we're not going to be
creating any memory on the fly.
All the memory that we're going to
use is already set up when we begin.
That presents sort of an issue, right?
What if we don't know how much memory
we're going to have when we get
started?
Maybe you're going to be asking
the user to give you a number
and they're going to generate
a hundred linked list object.
So they're going to generate hundreds
of something and you don't know that.
Or maybe they generate 200 or 400.
We wouldn't be able to
predict this in advance,
and so we need to use dynamic
memory allocation in order
to get new memory in our program
while the program is already running.
And that's a little bit different
than anything we've seen before.
We can do this by allocating memory
from something called the heap.
The heap is a giant pool of memory.
And so far, the only pool of
memory that we're familiar with
is called the stack.
But dynamically allocated memory comes
from the heap and statically allocated
memory-- which is anything that
you give a name to, typically,
like a variable name--
is going to be set up on the stack.
And anything that you create dynamically
while your program is running
is going to come from the heap.
But as we can see from this
diagram, the stack and the heap
are actually the same
big chunk of memory.
It just so happens that the stack we
allocate from the bottom to the top,
typically, to visualize it.
So the stack memory addresses will
be a bit lower numbers and the heap
will have higher numbers
and it'll allocate downward.
So it's really one giant pool of memory,
but we call it two different things
depending on how it's being used.
The stack for statically declared memory
grows up and the heap for dynamically
allocated memory grows down.
How do we get at this
dynamically allocated memory?
How do we access memory on the heap?
We need to use a new
function called malloc.
You can get malloc by pound
including standard lib.h, stdlib.h.
And the only argument that
you need to pass to malloc
is how many bytes of
memory that you want.
So if you want an
integer, you say malloc 4.
If you want a character, you malloc 1.
If you want to double,
you malloc 8, and so on.
And you can be more complex
than that, as we'll soon see.
What malloc will then try and
do is find some chunk of memory
the size that you asked for on the heap.
So it'll go and try and find
eight contiguous bytes of memory,
for example.
If we're allocating a double, it will go
and try and find eight contiguous bytes
of memory from the heap.
And what it will do is it will return
to you a pointer to that memory.
So the only way we're going to be able
to access dynamically allocated memory
or use it is by dereferencing the
pointer that we get back from malloc.
And that's why it's important
to understand pointers
before going forward.
Now, it's possible that
malloc might not actually
be able to give you back
memory, in which case
it's going to return to you null.
And so one of the first rules to
remember about dynamically allocated
memory is to always check
for null after malloc.
Now, why might this happen?
Maybe you've run out of memory.
The stack and the heap
have just completely
run out or there's been some
sort of catastrophic failure
that we can't predict.
But either way, if you recall
from our pointers video,
dereferencing a null pointer, bad news.
So the first thing you want to
do-- after you malloc, of course--
is to check to make sure that
you didn't get back null.
And if you did, you're going to need
to abort your program because something
has gone wrong and you can't proceed
with what you currently have.
So if we want to just get an
integer, statically declare it,
we can just say int x.
That's going to create a
variable called x on the stack
that we can then assign
any value that we like to.
If you want to dynamically
allocate an integer,
we say the following-- int
star px equals malloc 4.
And the reason we say
four here is because there
are four bytes in an integer.
I easily also could have used the sizeof
operator, which is available in C.
Basically, you pass it a type--
so it's a little bit different.
Usually with functions
you pass in a variable.
With malloc, you pass in--
or with sizeof, rather,
you pass in a type
and it will return how many bytes
that type takes up on the system.
So int star px equals malloc
size of int or int star ps
equals malloc 4 basically
means malloc going
to go try and find you
four bytes of memory that
are next to each other on the heap.
And malloc will return to you a
pointer to that memory called px.
And then we could
dereference that pointer,
as we've seen in the pointers video, to
manipulate it, to put a value in there,
to do whatever we want to do with it.
Let's see another example of this.
Maybe we want to get an
integer from the user.
So recall that CS50 we have the
get_int function that we can use.
Int x equals get_int.
We're basically prompting the
user for some integer value.
And it'll give us some
number, hopefully,
in this example, a positive number.
Let's say I want to declare an array
of that many floats on the stack.
I can do this by saying float
stack_array and then in square
brackets-- which, again,
indicates the size of the array--
x.
This is legal in C 99 and C 11.
If you're using a very
old version of C, this
was actually previously not allowed.
But you can do this.
We can basically get
a variable-sized array
on the stack, which we're doing
here because we don't know
how big it's going to be in advance.
We're just getting it from the user.
But this is how we would
declare an array of floats
on the stack where the
number of items in that array
is the number the user just gave us.
And I can also dynamically allocate
an array of floats on the heap--
not on the stack, remember,
because we're dynamically
allocating the memory this time.
Float star heap_array.
So that's my pointer to the
memory that I'm getting.
And I want to malloc x
times the size of a float.
So if I want to have 50 floats,
I need 50 times the size
of a float, so 50 times 4.
Maybe I want 100, so it
would be 100 times four.
So that's why we're doing
the multiplication there.
And malloc is going to return
to us one giant block of memory
that size, which we can then
just treat like any other array.
There's one catch with dynamically
allocated memory, though,
that we have to deal with, and that's
something that we haven't seen before,
and that is that it is not released
back to the system when you are done.
So if you haven't yet seen our video
on the call stack or stack frames,
this might not be something
you're aware of yet.
But typically, when a function
finishes running, what happens
is all of the memory that was created
for purposes of that function's
existence gets destroyed and it
is released back to the system
to be used somewhere else.
So another function call that might
come up can use that same bit of memory
before.
That's kind of convenient, right?
This system is constantly
recycling where it can.
But when you tell the system,
I want a block of memory,
the system is not going to
assume anything about it.
It's not going to assume that it
hasn't seen you make a call with it
for 50 lines or whatever, and it's
just going to dynamically free
it or release it back to the system.
And if you fail to release enough
memory back to the system, what you get
is something called a memory leak.
And memory leaks are really not
good because they can really
slow down your system.
And in fact, there
are some browsers that
shall remain nameless that are sort of
notorious for not freeing memory or not
releasing memory back to
the system when it's done.
And that can really cause
your computer to slow down
because that browser is basically
hogging a bunch of memory
and the other programs on
your computer can't use it
because the browser has sort
of allocated it and said,
no, this is mine.
I need it.
But it never releases
it back to be shared
by the other things on the system.
So that's why if you leave
a browser open for days--
or some browsers open
for days or weeks--
you might notice your
computer starts to slow down.
Now, the rule is, as
I've mentioned before,
when you're done working
with dynamically allocated
memory, all you have to do is free it.
And free is another function that
is available in standard lib.h.
And basically what you passed to
free is a pointer to any memory
that you have dynamically
allocated previously.
And basically that's just
telling the system, I'm done.
You can use this memory
for whatever you'd like.
So here's another
example let's say we want
to malloc a 50 character long array--
so basically a big string.
We're going to call it word.
We dynamically allocate it.
Then we just do some stuff with it.
Maybe we were in the
middle of a function.
You know, we're changing its value.
We're assigning new characters.
We're printing it out, for example.
And then we decide that
we're done with it.
How do we release this
back to the system?
We just need to free it.
So we free word.
Word is the pointer to
that block of memory.
That's the thing that we want to free.
So there are three basic
rules for malloc and free
that are really
important to internalize.
The first is that
everything that you malloc
has to be freed before your
program finishes running.
Now, granted, if your
program actually finishes
running, once it's completely done,
once you've returned zero from main,
for example, then it will be freed.
But it's a good practice to
make sure that everything
that you allocate you specifically
free by explicitly calling
the free function, as opposed just
relying on the system to do it
once your program is completely done.
So everything that you
malloc, you have to free.
Rule number two, only things that you
malloc are things that you should free.
So if you statically declared a
variable, you don't want to free it.
The system is going to
take care of releasing
all statically declared memory for you.
It's only dynamically allocated
memory-- only memory that you malloc
are things that you should free.
And then make sure not to free the
same block of memory more than once
because that can create the
problem of a double free
and you have sort of
an inverse memory leak,
like a memory flow or something, where
you tricked the system into thinking
that you have more memory than you do.
It's not the kind of thing
that you actually want to do.
So remember, everything
you malloc you should free.
Only things that you
malloc you should free.
And don't free anything more than once.
Let's just close this
video by taking a look
at a couple of lines of
code and a visual example
to show you exactly what's
happening as we do it.
So first, let's statically
declare an integer called m.
And so this would look
something like this.
I've colored the box green
because in my head, sort of,
integers are always in green boxes.
And I've written the label m on the box.
Then I'm going to say int star a.
So here I'm statically
declaring a pointer called a.
So recall that I like to think of
it's an int star, so it's int-like,
so it will be green.
It's a green-ish box.
It's not a green box
because that's for ints.
But int stars are sort of green-ish.
They refer to ints.
So this is another box
and this one is called a.
Then I can say int star b
equals malloc sizeof int.
So what's going to happen here?
Well, I'm going to have something
called b that I'm giving a name to.
So that's going to be sort
of a light greenish box.
And I'm asking malloc to dynamically
give me one int's worth of space.
And so what actually happened
sort of visually is this.
Notice that the actual integer
I didn't give a name to.
I don't have a name for it.
It's one way typically
that I know I don't
have a statically declared integer.
The only way that I can
refer to that green box
is by dereferencing
the pointer called b.
So b has a name, and
that's statically declared.
But I dereference b in order to get
to this dynamically allocated memory.
And of course, I'm not
going to do this here.
But the first thing I
should do immediately
after this is check to make
sure that b is not null.
If b is null, something
has gone wrong and I
need to stop my program immediately.
Next, I can say something like
this-- a equals ampersand m.
If you recall from
our video on pointers,
basically this just means a points to m.
So that just creates this arrow here.
Next up, let's say a equals b.
Before I show you what's
going to happen here,
can you try and guess a little
bit about what it's going to be?
Take a look at the diagram.
Think about how
relationships might change.
If I say a equals b, what am I saying?
What I'm saying is that a and b are now
going to point to the same location,
in particular, a is going to a
point where b currently points.
And so instead of
pointing to m, a is now
going to point over here to
this dynamically allocated
block that I can currently
only reference-- now
I can reference it multiple ways.
Now I could say star a or star b.
I can reference it either way
because both of those same statically
declared variables point
to the same location.
I can then say m equals 10.
That's not a problem because
10 was statically declared.
It's a box that I know about already.
It's got a name.
So when I say m equals
10, I'm just saying
put 10 into this green box called m.
Star b equals m plus 2.
It's a little weird, right?
But what's m plus 2?
Well, m is 10, so 10 plus 2 is 12.
And star b equals 12.
When I say a star b,
I'm dereferencing b.
So I'm going to travel along
the arrow to where b points.
And I'm going to put
12 in that location.
OK?
Next up I'm going to free b.
So remember what happens with free
is we are telling the system we're
no longer working with this.
We're done.
You can take these four bytes back,
or whatever the size of it is.
This one happens to be four bytes.
You can take it back
and use it for whatever
you want in some other program.
So when I free b, this
memory basically goes away.
a and b still point to where it used to
be, but I no longer have access to it.
If I try and touch it, the
system might get upset with me.
So for example, if I try and say this--
star a equals 11--
what's going to happen?
Unpredictable behavior.
We don't know.
We might get a segmentation
fault because we're
touching memory that we're no longer--
we don't have write
privileges to anymore.
You might get away with it, depends
on where that memory happened
to live on the system.
But it's unpredictable.
So once you free memory, remember,
you're telling the system,
I don't need it anymore.
So if you then try and use it,
some strange things might result.
Dynamic memory allocation
is a little strange
to get used to because we're so used
this idea of creating a variable
and assigning it a value and
just manipulating it in that way
that using pointers to sort
of control where memory is
and change it indirectly through
pointers can be a bit strange.
But just keep practicing with it.
Internalize those rules about how
to malloc and free successfully
to make sure that you don't create
memory leaks or anything like that.
And you should be off to a good start.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.