DOUG LLOYD: So at this
point, we're pretty
familiar with all of
the data types that come
native to C. We have characters, and
floats, and integers, and doubles,
and we're also familiar now with the
CS50 data types of strings and Booles.
But that doesn't limit
everything that we can do.
We surely can do more.
Indeed, with structures,
that gives us an ability
to start to define our
own data types that
might be useful for our own programs.
What's cool about
structures is they allow
us to unify many different
variables of different data types
into a single brand new type.
And we can give that new
type its own unique type
name as a way to identify it.
This isn't the first time
we've seen the ability
to combine multiple variables together.
We've seen that with arrays.
Remember, the restriction with
arrays is that we can only
combine things of the same type.
We can have a whole bunch of
integers or a whole bunch of floats.
But we can't mix them up.
With structures, we actually can.
We can group together logical--
we can group together elements that have
a logical connection to one another.
So for example, we can
group together a structure
for say a student, where
a student would have an ID
number, which is probably an integer.
But they also have a
name, which is a string.
And they might have a
GPA, which is a float.
And we can have all of these
things tied together in basically
what's a super variable.
It's a variable that has
other variables within it.
The way to do this in C is
actually pretty straightforward.
Some syntax might look like this.
Instead of a student in this
example, let's use a car.
We introduced the concept of
a structure by saying, struct.
We're about to define a structure type.
And in particular, we're
going to define a struct car.
And struct car actually
now becomes our type name.
It's not just car.
It's struct car.
Inside of the curly braces
from this point forward,
we can define all of
the different variables
that we want inside
of our super variable.
So for example, here are some
things that are common to cars.
They have a year, the year
they were manufactured.
We have a model, and a license
plate, and an odometer, which
is a number of miles, and
maybe they have an engine size,
which in the United States
is usually represented
as a float for how many
leaders the engine capacity is.
And notice that these are all different
data types being mixed together.
We have integers, and
we have two strings,
and we have a float, or a double all
mixed up inside of one super variable.
To finish our definition
of the structure,
we have a closing curly brace.
And then really important,
a common syntax error
is a semicolon at the
end, which completes
our definition of a struct car.
Once we define the
structure, and usually we
define our structure at
the very top of our program
up near our pound includes,
and our pound defines,
but we also might define
them in a separate dot H file
because maybe we're using this type
definition in several different files,
or several different programs.
And so it makes sense to define
it somewhere outside of one--
outside of a single file and have
it be a dot H file that we can pound
include in multiple different contexts.
Now we have effectively created this
new type and we can start to use it.
And we can create variables
of this type just like we
can create variables of any other type.
Int x, that's how we
create an integer called x.
Struct car y, that's how we create a
variable called y of type struct car.
So that's how we create
the variable overall.
How do we create the individual
fields, or members of that?
Or rather, how do we access the
individual fields or members
of that structure?
We can do so using something
called the dot operator.
Let's take a look at
what that looks like.
So the top here, I have
a variable declaration.
Struct car, my car.
Again, here the type is struct car.
And the variable name is my car.
From this point forward, whenever
I want to refer to a field,
or a member within my car, which
is again, the variable name,
I can use the dot operator to access
those individual fields within my car.
So I can say, for example,
mycar.year equals 2011.
I can't just say year equals 2011.
Year is something that
is part of my car.
So I have to always refer to
it in the context of my car.
I can say strcpy(mycar.plate, "CS50").
Remember, it's a string.
I can't just assign it.
I have to copy that
string into the variable.
I can say, mycar.odometer equals 50505
or anything else that I want to do.
I can set the engine size,
and I can set the model.
I can do whatever else I
want to do just by accessing
the fields similar to this.
But structures like variables
of all other data types,
we don't have to just
use the stack for this.
We don't just have to say
struct car, my car, semicolon.
We could dynamically
allocate this if we don't
know at the beginning of
our program, for example,
that we're going to need a
certain number of these things.
We can just declare this on the fly
dynamically using pointers of course.
In order to access our
fields in that situation,
we don't use just the
dot operator because we
have a pointer to a structure.
We also have to first, as you may
recall, dereference that pointer
and then access its fields.
It adds a little bit of extra stuff,
but let's take a look again here.
So here now, instead of statically
declaring a struct car called my car,
I'm going to dynamically allocate
a struct car called my car.
So struct car star my car, and then I'm
going to malloc space for a struct car.
And here's a cool thing about size of.
Size of is not just built in.
It doesn't just happen to know just the
size of integers, characters, floats,
and doubles.
It can also figure out on the
fly exactly how much space
is required for a struct car.
So you don't have to go through
and figure out, OK, well, this
is probably like 30 bytes or something.
You can just say, size
of struct car, and let
the computer figure it out for you.
So struct car star my car equals
malloc size of struct car.
That dynamically allocates on the
heap one chunk of memory large enough
to hold a single struct car within it.
And then I can access my fields by
first dereferencing the pointer.
And then once I've
dereferenced the pointer,
I can then use the dot
operator to access the fields.
Again, it's very similar
to what we just saw.
But the syntax here is
a little cumbersome.
Now we have extra parentheses, we
have this star, we have this dot,
surely there's got to be an easier way.
C programmers love for there
to be easier ways to do things.
And in fact, there is
a shortcut for this.
It so happens that accessing the
field of a structure via its pointer
is a common enough operation that there
is an entirely different operator that
allows us to do this
much more succinctly.
And it is called the
arrow operator, which
is a hyphen and then
a greater than symbol,
literally making it
look like it's an arrow.
It does two operations back to back.
So for the first thing it does is
it dereferences the pointer, which
is on the left of the arrow.
And then it's going to access the field,
which is on the right of the arrow.
So for example, this is what
the code looked like before.
This is what we just had
on the slide a second ago
where I'm dereferencing pointers.
And then I'm using the dot
operator to access the fields.
Here is what the same code would
look like with the arrow syntax.
And the same thing is happening here.
The first thing I'm doing
is I'm dereferencing my car.
But the arrow operator does that for me.
I don't have to use the star syntax.
It just knows if I
have an arrow there, I
need to first dereference
the thing on the left,
and then I can access
the field on the right.
So using the arrow
operator is a great way
to have a shorthand for accessing the
field of a structure to which you only
have a pointer.
And you'll probably
use this a fair amount.
So it's syntax definitely to
befriend and to get used to.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.