[MUSIC PLAYING]
DOUG LLOYD: So in our
video on JavaScript,
we introduced you to the
concept of an object.
And in this video, I want to
talk about a very specific object
that we can use to manipulate data
and content on our web pages called
the document object.
Now, you may recall from that
discussion in the JavaScript video
that objects contain two
different things, basically.
They contain something
called properties or data.
And they contain methods,
which are functions
that apply just to those objects.
But what we didn't really
get into a lot of detail
was that those objects, what you can
put in them is actually pretty flexible.
You can do a lot of
different things with them.
You can not only put data in there.
You can also put other objects
or arrays inside of it.
And maybe those objects that you
put inside of that bigger object
also have other objects in them.
So you can kind of create this
nesting structure of objects
within a single
JavaScript object, which,
if you think about it, thinking back
to our discussion about C and trees,
it kind of creates a tree structure
where you have one object,
inside of that there's another one,
inside of those, there's other ones,
and so on.
One very specific object in JavaScript
is called the document object.
And that is an object
that basically organizes
the entire content of a single web
page into a single JavaScript object.
And once you know the methods and
properties of the document object,
you can change them in JavaScript.
You can assign the different
properties to a value.
You can call methods on the object to
change some of those properties, which
then allow you to manipulate the
content or look and feel of your website
only using JavaScript, instead of
going back and editing your HTML
or the Python that underlies it.
So here's an example of a
very simple HTML website.
There's really not much going on here.
But as you can see, there's HTML tags.
We have inside of that
a head and a body.
Inside of the head, we have
a title, "Hello, world."
Inside of the body, we have a
couple of different tags there.
We have an H2, or a second-level header
tag, a paragraph tag, and a link.
And all of this can actually
be represented in JavaScript
as a document object.
We can actually arrange
all of this hierarchically,
sort of similar to what we're doing with
the indentation, where clearly things
that are indented one level further
in are nested with inside of another--
nested inside of another
part of the HTML.
So for example, here is what a
tree structure of that simple web
page we just looked at might be.
So we have a document.
And inside of that, we have HTML.
And that's kind of represented
by the HTML tag that we have.
And everything inside of it is sort
of nested below it, as you can see.
Within our HTML, there are two
main things at the next level down.
There is the head and the body.
So we can look specifically at the head.
And we see that inside of
the head, there is a title.
And inside of the title, there
is some text, "Hello, world."
And we can also look at the body,
which is an entirely different segment
of the object or of the
tree, inside of which
is each of those three individual
pieces, the h2, the p, and the a tag.
And all of that can
be represented sort of
in a tree, which maps,
as you can see, as I'm
highlighting the text in green on the
HTML, to a section of our HTML as well.
So the document object has properties,
just like any other object.
And it has a number of methods as well.
And if you, again--
and we're going to talk
about this in just a moment--
know how to navigate through the
document object, starting at the top
and drilling down to the section
of the page that you want,
you can change what
your site looks like.
So actually, let's go into
the IDE and take a look
at how you can see the document
object yourself in the browser.
OK.
So we're in my IDE and I'm
really quickly just going
to show you that this is exactly the
same HTML that we had just a moment ago
on a slide.
And I have page actually
open in another tab here.
And you'll also notice that I
popped open my Developer Console.
If you're using Google
Chrome, you can usually
do that with Control-Shift-J on
a PC, or Command-Shift-J a Mac.
And that just opens
the JavaScript Console.
And recall from our
JavaScript video that we
can use the Console using
console.log, for instance,
to print out information to the Console
as we're going through our page.
Well, there's other things we
can do with the Console as well.
We can also type commands to
it to have it do something.
And so what I'm going to do this time
is something a little bit different.
Instead of typing console.log,
I'm going to type console.dir.
And what console.dir
is going to do is it's
going to basically try and
organize the content of my page
here in a directory
structure, which basically
is a fancy way of describing an object.
So we can kind of look and
see what's in the object.
And what object do I want to look at?
Well, I want to look
at the document object,
so I'm going to console.dir document.
And when I hit Enter here, we're
going to see that I got an undefined.
But above that I have this
sort of pound sign document.
That is the JavaScript Console
returning to me the document object.
When this pops open, there's going
to be a lot of stuff in there.
And a lot of it we're not
going to really talk about.
I just want to show you how things
are nested in that document object.
So I'm going to pop this open.
And again, there's a lot of stuff here.
But what I really want
to take a look at is
the children, so just looking at the
children property of the document
object.
And you can see that there is one.
If I pop that open,
what do you see here?
Inside of the document
object, there is one child
called HTML, which you might recall
from our diagram a few slides ago.
If I pop that open,
you'll see that it also
has children, two of them
in fact, head and body.
And I can continue doing this
exercise all the way down.
But in fact, if I kept doing that
and I looked inside of the head,
I'd find the title tag.
I could open that and
see what's in there.
Inside of the body I would find that
there are three children, the h2,
the p, and the a tag.
All of them are nested inside
of this big document object.
And we can actually manipulate
this object using JavaScript.
Let's go back to the slides
and talk a little bit
about how we might be able to do that.
So again, the document
object, as you could
see from when we were just looking
at it in the Console, is pretty big.
There's a lot of stuff in there.
We're not going to cover all
of it, because not all of it's
going to be really necessary as
you get started working with it.
But I want to cover a
couple of the big properties
that you might use when you're working
with the document object, as well
as a couple of the
methods in just a moment.
So one of them, for
example, is InnerHTML, which
holds the HTML inside of a set of tags.
So for example, the
InnerHTML of the title tag,
if I was to go into
that section, would be
"Hello, world" or whatever I called--
whatever my actual title of my page is.
That's the InnerHTML of the
title tag or the title node
or the title object within
the overall document object.
nodeName similarly would just be title
for the node we were just describing,
or the section of the object
we were just describing.
Id.
You may recall from our
video on HTML and CSS
that we can specify an optional ID
attribute to certain HTML elements.
We usually use this
in the context of CSS,
for example, to style
one particular node
or one particular set of tags in
our HTML with a certain style.
We can give it an ID so that the
CSS knows which section of the page
to apply that style to.
So this property would
just allow us to figure out
what the ID of that particular node is.
parentNode is a reference
to the node one level up.
So again, if I'm looking
at the title node--
I'll just continue using
that example for now--
the parent node of that would be
head, because title is nested inside
of head in that tree structure.
childNodes is sort of
the converse of that.
It is what is down from
where I currently am.
So if I am now using the
body node as an example,
so we've kind of nested to
that section of the tree,
the child nodes of the body node would
be that h2 and that p and that a.
Those would be the three
child nodes from that area.
attributes, an array of
attributes of an HTML element.
A good example here is the image tag.
So if I am, again, navigating through
the document object using JavaScript
and I come to an image tag and I want
to figure out what attributes it has,
well, you may recall that
an image's attributes
include, for example, its source.
What is the source file?
Or perhaps I've also specified optional
parameters of height and width.
Those would all the attributes
associated with that particular node
of the document object.
And then style, which is one way--
which is another way we can actually
style the look and feel of a page.
And in a few moments,
we'll actually be going
through an example,
where we specifically
manipulate this property, the style
property, to change something.
But it is analogous to the CSS
styling of a particular section
or portion of the page.
So those are some of the
most common properties.
There are also four common
methods that you might see.
And again, there are
many more beyond this.
But here are four that you
might use as you're beginning
to work with the document object.
getElementById.
And notice that now because
we're talking about methods,
these are all functions that
may optionally take parameters.
In this case, we're looking for
an element with a specific ID.
That's the parameter
being passed in there.
So if we maybe have styled a
particular element using CSS
and we've given it that
optional ID attribute,
this method would go and navigate
through the entire document
object for us and find
that specific node,
one of those further down the tree
or further nested within the object.
It would find that section
of the page and return to you
the M object from that point down.
getElementsByTagName.
Notice it's getElements.
This would, for example, maybe find all
of the instances of me using a B tag.
So it would give me an array of all of
the bold tagged sections of my site.
appendChild basically allows
me to add an additional node
below where I currently am, so it allows
me to expand the number of things.
I might want to add a new element on the
fly to the body portion of my website.
I can append perhaps a
new paragraph tag or an H3
or something else that wasn't there
before using this method here.
And then removeChild is sort
of the opposite of that.
It deletes a section
of the page by removing
that portion of the HTML, that entire
node, from the document object.
I do want to point out
one thing here that causes
programmers a lot of heartache.
I know it's caused me
a lot of heartache.
When you're using the getElementById
attribute, notice that the D in Id
is lowercase.
Usually when we use the term ID for
identification, it's usually capital I,
capital D. I can't even tell you
how many times I have accidentally
typed capital I, capital D here.
And then I get a JavaScript
error, because it
doesn't know what I'm talking about.
So calling this out specifically
as a well-known common issue,
be really careful when using this
to use a lowercase D there instead.
So because the document
object is one big thing
with lots of objects nested
within it, if we start at the top,
we can find our way using
those properties and methods
to any other area within
the document object.
Now, you may have seen that some of
those terms, some of those property
names and some of those method
names are really, really long.
It would be a lot to
type out to do that.
And so it's actually
quite common when you
are working on a project that has a
lot of document object manipulation
to use a JavaScript
library called jQuery.
jQuery is quite popular.
It's probably the most popular
JavaScript library currently in use.
It's been around for about 10 years now.
It's an open source library.
And it does a lot of things.
But one of the things it
does particularly well
is simplify what's called
client-side scripting,
or where you are writing some code
to change things on your computer
to affect the look and feel of a site.
Document object manipulation is one
of those things it does really well.
And it also does AJAX
queries, which we'll
talk about in another video
on AJAX, quite well also.
So for example, the
raw JavaScript version
of this, what we're doing
here in this raw JavaScript
is changing one section of the page.
I'm finding the element of
my page whose ID is colorDiv.
So I'm starting from
the top of the document.
It's going to look through the
entire document object, all of those
nested nodes below it, to find a
section of the page called colorDiv.
And I'm going to go there and set that
node's style property's backgroundColor
property to green.
So basically, all
that's happening here is
I'm changing the background color
of one section of my page to green.
That is a lot to type to
do that in pure JavaScript.
In jQuery, the trade-off
is you get a shorter--
you have to type less stuff.
You have a shorter line of code.
But it's going to look
a little bit more weird.
So this would do exactly the
same thing using jQuery syntax.
The dollar sign is a shorthand
way of saying jQuery.
And it's going to be looking for a
section of my page called colorDiv.
That's the jQuery syntax for it.
And I'm going to change that node's
CSS background color to green.
Again, it's a little bit strange.
But it is a shorter way
to do the same thing.
So you will often see this as opposed
to the longer JavaScript version
when you're seeing some
client-side scripting.
What I want to do now
is go back into the IDE
and show you a little bit about how--
show you a couple of examples of how
we can actually manipulate the document
object using JavaScript
and jQuery to change
the color of a section of a web page.
All right.
So here is a very simple web page--
and you can download this example when
you're reviewing this video--
that has a whole bunch
of different buttons.
And as you can see at the top, there's
a section that says "Change my color!"
We're going to be trying
to change the background
color of that section of the page.
And apparently, I'm going to
do it four different ways.
There's individual functions for
background color written in JavaScript;
a single function to change
the background color,
so a bit of a design improvement
perhaps; an event handler--
recall from the end of
our video on JavaScript,
we talked a little bit
about event handlers,
so this will be another opportunity
to see those in action--
and one example where we do the exact
same thing using jQuery instead of
using raw JavaScript.
So let's take a look at what the code
for this site actually looks like.
In my IDE we'll open this tab.
As you can see, I'm loading a couple
of different JavaScript scripts
at the beginning of my
page, so I'm basically
doing a pound include,
the analogy here from C,
of a couple of JavaScript files.
And I have one file for each of the four
different types of color manipulation
we're going to do.
And then here, it's not
particularly well designed HTML,
but it kind of gets the job done.
I have one section with a set of five
buttons for the background color ones,
one for the passing in the color as a
parameter, one for the event handler,
and one for the jQuery ones.
And they all look a
little bit different.
So let's start by looking at
the individual color ones.
So there's really not much to this.
You saw that I wrote those
five different functions,
turn purple, turn green, turn
orange, turn red, and turn blue.
And all they do is,
using pure JavaScript,
they get the element by ID of colorDiv,
which is the element that we're trying
to change the background color of.
And I set it's style
backgroundColor attribute
to purple, green, orange,
red or blue, as described.
So that's hopefully the most obvious.
Then we have sort of
a general purpose one,
where instead we're passing
in a color as a parameter.
So you may recall, looking back at
our HTML for a second, for that one
I'm passing in the colors purple, green,
orange, red, and blue as parameters
to that function.
And in the general purpose
one, I'm just saying
whatever I passed in as a parameter,
set the colorDiv's backgroundColor
to that color instead.
Then we have the event handler on.
So recall-- if we take a look
at the event handler one,
the line looks exactly the
same for all five of them.
But you might remember from our
discussion on event handlers
that the way an event handler works
is when you click on a button,
for instance, the event handler
captures some information
about what triggered it to happen.
So it knows, for example,
which button you clicked.
And all of those buttons--
I'm going to jump again
to the HTML for a second.
All of those buttons have a different
title, purple, green, orange, red,
and blue, with the
capital letters there,
that is the word that is actually
going to appear on the button.
So I have a little bit of a way to
distinguish between all of them.
But as it turns out-- sorry about that.
As it turns out, in order for
my color changing to work,
I can't pass in a capital
letter color name.
I have to pass in a lowercase one.
So what I'm going to do instead is
I'm going to set the document's--
the colorDiv's backgroundColor
to whatever object
triggered the event to be
called in the first place.
I'm going to look at its InnerHTML-- so
here's that InnerHTML property coming
into play.
And what I'm going to do to it is
transform that entire string, so
that capital P purple, into lowercase.
So basically what happens here
is when I click on a button,
say I click on the purple
button, what is happening
is that capital P purple is being
turned into all lowercase purple.
And then that word "purple" is
going to become the color that I'm
setting the backgroundColor to.
So hopefully that makes sense.
Again, what I'm doing is
I'm clicking on a button.
That button has a title.
I'm just taking the
title of that button,
the InnerHTML turmoil between the
button tags, making it all lowercase.
And that is then a color that I
can assign the backgroundColor to.
Again, you might play
with this yourself when
you're tinkering if you're
following along with this video
and maybe set some other
different colors to see
that you can make this change as well.
And then we have the
jQuery version of this.
And we'll take a look at the
HTML again for a second here.
Notice with this one, it
looks a little bit different.
I'm not specifying an
onClick attribute this time.
I'm creating a new class
called a jQuery button.
But there seems to be no
function that gets called.
Well, that's kind of a side effect
of what is happening in jQuery.
And the way jQuery works-- or
one of the ways jQuery can work
is that we can do something like this.
This uses anonymous functions.
Remember from JavaScript that we have
this notion of anonymous functions.
We can have functions
that don't have names.
So what's happening here is when the
document-- there's that word "document"
again--
when the document object
is fully loaded or ready,
the page is going to execute
the following function.
It's going to say, I'm going to
look for every instance of something
being of class--
that's what the little dot
there, remember that from CSS--
of class JQ button appears on the page.
And when any of those
buttons is clicked,
I'm going to execute this
other anonymous function that
is going to do basically what we
just saw in the final example there,
where we transformed the entire
text of the button into lowercase
and that becomes a color
name that we can assign.
But I'm just going to do it using jQuery
syntax instead of JavaScript syntax.
So again, what is happening here is
the document, the page is fully loaded.
And when the page is fully
loaded, the following function
is applied to the page.
Every jQuery button is
given this extra attribute,
this onClick attribute,
such that when you click it,
it assigns a color based on
whatever the text is of the button.
Again, we're not going to get into
a lot of detail on jQuery itself.
That's sort of an exercise for at home.
But this version that you're
seeing here is exactly
the same as the event handler version
we just saw for pure JavaScript,
except written in jQuery style.
And if I actually go to the page,
all four of these do in fact work.
I can click the purple one
here, the green one here.
I can click the orange one, red one.
They all do the exact same thing.
They just do it doing
a couple of different--
using a couple of different techniques.
So you can hopefully use
this example to give yourself
a better understanding of
using functions in JavaScript,
using events in JavaScript,
and perhaps dipping
your toe in the water of jQuery.
So if you want to learn more about
jQuery beyond what we talk about
in this video, you can go
to the jQuery documentation,
which is available at the website
you see on the screen here.
It's a great place to go to learn about
some of the more interesting things
that you can do with jQuery.
And we'll see a little bit more about
this in our video on AJAX as well.
I'm Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.