DOUG LLOYD: So in our
videos on web development,
we've talked a couple of times
now about what a database is.
And in this video, we're goingww
to get into a bit more detail
and show you exactly what a
database is, why we would use it,
and how we might manipulate it.
In order for us to build websites that
are sort of more complex than just
a page where they just go
and see news, for example,
we might need a database
to store information,
such as username and
password combinations
so that a user attempts to log in.
That log-in information
is sent to the database.
It is checked against
information in the database
to see whether that username-password
combination matches.
And if so, it lets the user in.
We might also store other stuff for
users, like their shopping history
or really any other
information that you might
want to keep long-term for a user.
Now, if you ever used programs like
Microsoft Excel or Google Sheets
or Numbers, you're probably familiar
with the basic idea of a database.
A database consists of a couple
of different levels of hierarchy.
Within a database, we have tables.
And within each of those tables,
we have rows and columns.
And if you are familiar with Excel,
or perhaps even if you're not,
let's take a quick second and
I can draw this analogy for you
about what a database, a
table, a row, a column is.
And then we can translate that in
just a moment to the same idea in SQL.
So on my screen here, I've
opened up an Excel file.
And across the top here, you
see I have these letters--
A, B, C, D, E. These would be
different columns in my file.
Down the left side, I have numbered
rows, where I might put information.
So, for example, I might just
put my name here in cell A1.
So it's in the A column
in the first row.
Now, down at the bottom
left is a feature
that you may not have used too much if
you don't use Excel very frequently.
But there's these notions of sheets.
Sheets are sort of akin
to different tables.
Notice that when I switch to sheet 2,
the data that was in sheet 1, my name,
is no longer there.
So each sheet has its own
unique set of rows and columns.
But all of these sheets are still bound
up in one single file called Book 1.
So the analogy here is that
Book 1 is our database, which
contains a different number of
tables, which in Excel parlance
is just a sheet.
And each sheet has columns
that we can put data in
and rows that we can
put data in, as well.
So there are a couple of different
types of database engines
that we can use in our programs.
We're going to talk about SQL, S-Q-L,
which stands for the Structured Query
Language.
The Structure Query Language
is a programming language
whose sole purpose in life is to query
or ask questions of or retrieve data
from a database.
And there are many different
implementations of SQL.
Two of the most popular
are as follows-- we have
MySQL which is an open-source platform.
It is very commonly used to
establish relational databases.
We're not going to get
into a lot of detail
in this video about what
a relational database is
versus other types of database.
But just know that there
are more than one type,
and we cover relational
databases in this course.
Another type, which we actually
have used in CS50 since 2016,
is SQLite, which has a very
similar feature set to MySQL.
But it's just a little more lightweight.
It's a little easier to use on CS50 IDE.
And so that's why we're actually going
to be using that one in the class.
Now, regardless of which implementation
of SQL that you use, a lot of them
will come with a tool called phpMyAdmin,
which is a GUI or Graphical User
Interface tool that is
used to execute some
of the more tedious or mundane database
queries in a more user-m friendly way
because you can just click and
do things in the web browser.
And those are most commonly used to
build databases in the first place
and to set up tables because
that's the first thing you're
going to do once you get your database
configured, is to create a table.
Because without a table, we
have no rows and columns.
And without rows and columns,
we can't store any data.
Tables have very cumbersome syntax
that is used to set them up.
And so using phpMyAdmin, the graphical
interface, to build your table
is definitely gonna come in handy.
In the process of building
your table, you're
going to have to specify
exactly which columns
are going to be stored in that table.
So at the very beginning, when
you create your table, you say,
my table's going to store
usernames and passwords
and whatever sort of other
information you want.
and you have to specify that before you
have inserted any data into the table.
So you have to design ahead of time
what your table is going to look like.
Once you've done that, pretty
much every query except for, like,
deleting the database
and deleting the table
that you're going to use
on that table going forward
is going to refer to
data which is stored
in the different rows of the table.
Just like in C, every
column of our SQL table
is capable of holding data
of different data types.
So in C, for example, we had characters
and strings and integers and floats.
And SQL has a few more
data types than that.
This is just 20 of them, and this
is not even an exhaustive list.
But some of these things
should look familiar.
So, for example, we have int,
which can store integers.
But we also have these four other
types, which can hold integers
with different upper bounds.
So you may recall from C that
the upper bound of integer
is 2 to the 31st power, or 2 to the
32nd power if they're unsigned integers.
But here we can say
small ints or tiny ints
or medium or big ints,
each of which have
different upper bounds on the values.
Decimal and float stand in
place of double and float,
which we're familiar with from C. We
can also store date and time stamps
in SQL databases.
There's no data type for
that that's native to C.
But in SQL, there are a couple
of different ways to do this.
We can even do more exotic things
like store geometry or line strings.
And what are these?
Well, geometry and line strings can
be used to store in a SQL database
a mapping out or a drawing out of an
area on a map, such as using GIS data.
And we can actually store
that in our SQL table
and recreate that exact
drawing a little bit later on.
Text sort of stands in
the stead of strings
for just arbitrarily
large chunks of text.
Enums are also a type that exists in C,
but we don't talk about them too much
in C. But really quickly, what an enum
is is it is a column of your table
that can be used to store
a limited set of values.
So, for example, I could
have an enum that is called,
like, favorite colors, for example.
And I could specify when
I'm building my table
that it can only be capable of
holding red, green, and blue.
If you tried to insert a row
that had purple in that place,
that wouldn't work because it is not
one of the enumerated values that
can be stored in that column.
There are also char and varchar.
And these are not quite the same as
what you might think they are in C.
So let's just take a
quick second to explain
the difference between these two data
types, which are pretty important.
So unlike in C, char does not
refer to a single character.
It is actually sort of akin
to our notion of a string,
but with a caveat that that
string is a fixed length.
And typically when we specify
a char or a varchar type,
we have to specify the length
of that string at the outset,
just like we do in c.
So, for example, my column
type might be a char 10.
That means that I can
store 10 character strings
in that column of my table,
exactly 10 character strings.
So if I tried to store,
for example, the word
"hi," H-I, which is just two letters,
that would go into the column OK.
But it would also store 8 extra--
the equivalent of null bytes, basically,
so that I still had 10 characters,
per se, in that column for that row.
And if I tried to store,
like, a 15-character string,
that wouldn't work.
I'd only end up storing
the first 10 letters.
So it's always going
to be 10, every time.
A varchar, on the other hand,
refers to a variable-length string.
So if I said that my
column was varchar 99,
I can store 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 character
strings, up to 99 characters
long, without having to have all
of this extra sort of slack space
or null bytes or zeros
tacked onto the end.
So char, fixed-length strings.
Varchar, variable-length strings.
We won't get into the
difference between why
you might want to use one or the other.
But there are reasons why you might
not always want to use a varchar,
and you might want to use
a char in some situations.
Now, SQLite actually has many
or all of these same data types.
But the difference there is
that each of those data types
is affiliated with what's called a
type affinity to simplify things.
So that whole list of 20--
or more, really-- can be reduced to one
of these five different affinities--
null, integer, real, text, and blob.
Null is probably pretty
obvious-- nothing.
Integer-- whole numbers.
Real-- that would include
things like decimal and float.
Text would include things
like char and varchar.
Blob is just-- that would be more like
the geometry or data that isn't really
text, but it's just a large
number of bits or bytes.
That would be a blob.
And everything can reduce to one of
these five different type affinities.
So after specifying the columns, it's
also really important in our SQL table
to have one other
consideration, which is to have
one column which is our primary key.
Why do we need a primary key?
The reason is every row
of our table, in order
to make our SQL queries most effective,
should be able to be uniquely
and quickly identified.
So choosing the right
primary key will allow
us to make sure that there is one value
in every row that is completely unique.
And if that is true, if there is one
column in every row that's unique,
then we can uniquely identify
or very quickly identify
which row we're talking about.
Now, it's also possible to
establish a joint primary key,
which is just a combination
of, say, two columns--
but it can be an arbitrarily
large number of columns--
that is always guaranteed to be unique.
So I could have one column that
could always have A's or B's or C's.
I could have another column that has
ones and twos and threes and fours.
I could have multiple A's and multiple
B's and multiple C's, multiple ones,
twos, and threes.
But across all of those
rows, I'm only ever allowed
to have 1 combination of A1.
I can have B1, C1.
I can have A2, A3, A4.
But there's only ever one combination
of those two columns that is unique.
That would also be acceptable
because that is a joint primary key.
Now, SQL is a programming language,
like other programming languages
that we've discussed.
But it has a very limited vocabulary.
Now, there are more things that
you can do with SQL than we're
going to talk about in this
video because in this video
we're just going to talk
about the four operations
that one can perform on a table, or
the four main operations that you'll
most likely perform on the table--
INSERT, SELECT, UPDATE, and DELETE.
And these four things we'll get into a
bit more detail in just a second about.
But these are definitely
the most common four things
you'll be doing with the
tables that you're building,
certainly in CS50, but also probably
more generally whenever you're
working with databases.
So for all of the examples that
we're going to cover in this video,
we're going to consider
a database that contains
these two tables called users and moms.
And you can see users has four different
columns-- idnum, username, password,
and fullname.
And moms has two different
columns, username and mother.
And let's now start to
work with these and see
how we can manipulate this database
and the tables within it to--
for whatever reason we need them
to-- be updated in our website.
So the first operation
we'll cover is insert.
And as you might expect, it
adds information to a table.
Now, SQL queries have a
certain structure to them.
And so with each of these
operations, what I'm going to do
is give you the general sort of skeleton
of what a query might look like.
And then we'll use a couple
of examples of that query
to see how it affects our table.
So an insert query, in general,
looks something like this--
INSERT INTO table.
So we specify what table
we want to insert into.
And then we have
parentheses, columns-- which
is a comma-separated list of
all of the columns of our table
that we want to insert data into.
Then we have VALUES, and then a
comma-separated list of the values
that we want to put into those
columns in the same order.
So for example, I might want to INSERT
INTO users into these three columns--
username, password, name.
The values, respectively--
newman, in lowercase, USMAIL--
that's going to be
corresponding to the password--
and then capital-N Newman for fullname.
So assuming that I execute this
query on the users table shown here,
what's going to happen?
Well, this is what's going to happen.
We're going to add this row because
we inserted into the users table.
But you might be asking
yourself, wait a minute.
You never specified ID number.
So how exactly did ID number get there?
I mean, you specified newman
and USMAIL and Newman.
But that 12, that was
never part of our query.
And you're right.
Because when you define the
column that ultimately ends up
being your table's primary
key, it's usually a good idea
to have that column be an integer.
It's not a requirement, but
it's usually a good idea.
And because having a
primary key is so important,
you might want to specify
it to autoincrement.
And what this basically
means is you can forget
to include it as part of your query.
And if you do, it will
automatically insert a value there
that is unique from every
other value in that column,
typically by just incrementing
by one every time,
so that that row is still
guaranteed to be unique.
Because if it wasn't
set to autoincrement
and we just forgot to
omit it, there might
be a couple of rows that are
actually blank or null there.
But if that's our primary key,
if ID number is our primary key,
and we have a couple of rows that are
blank there, now they're not unique.
We have two rows that are blank.
We can't uniquely identify them.
And so when you set up your primary key,
you usually want it to be an integer,
and you usually want it to
autoincrement so that you can completely
forget about having to worry about
that and let the table do it for you.
So that's how 12 got there.
I had specified my idnum column
do autoincrement every time I
make an insert into the table.
Let's do this another time.
Let's insert into the other
table, insert into the moms table,
the following values into
these following columns.
We can INSERT INTO the username and
mother columns of the users table
the VALUES kramer and Babs Kramer.
And just like what we saw before, this
is what we would have as a result.
We would just insert that
row, and it would now
be part of our database
and part of our tables.
So that's the insert operation.
Now let's talk about the second
operation, which is select.
So if insert is used to put
information into a table,
select is used to get that
information back out of the table
so that we can do something with it.
Select queries also have
a very similar skeleton.
And they look like this--
SELECT and then whatever
columns you want
to choose FROM whichever table
you want to choose them from.
And then optionally in red
here, these two other things--
WHERE some condition is satisfied.
And we usually, in the context of SQL,
refer to a condition as a predicate.
But basically, we're just checking
to see that some situation is true.
And we might want to, for example,
order them by a specific column so
that they are organized alphabetically
by the values in some column
or whatever else.
We don't have to do
either WHERE or ORDER BY.
But generally WHERE
in particular is going
to be used so that you don't
get your entire database back.
And ORDER BY just helps to keep
things a little more organized.
So, for example, here's a
select query that we could use--
SELECT idnum, fullname
from the users table.
So let's see what's
going to happen here.
So remember, I'm selecting idnum
and fullname from the users table.
Well, what is the select
query going to return to me?
This information here.
It's going to look at
each row of the table,
and it's going to just pull out
the ID number and the full name
and give me all of those
down the entire users table.
My user table only
consists of three rows,
so it's given me three
pairs of information,
three idnum-fullname combinations.
Now let's say I want
to restrict my search
a little bit, my query a little bit.
SELECT password FROM users
WHERE idnum is less than 12.
So now I'm adding a predicate or
a condition to my select query.
What's going to happen here?
Well, I'm going to get this information.
This is just the password
column from the users table
where the ID number in
that row is less than 12.
So only rows 10 and 11's
password get given back to me.
12's does not because
12 is not less than 12.
There's one other thing we can do with
a select query, and that's to select *.
SELECT * from moms where
username equals jerry.
* is just shorthand for every column.
So instead of having to specify
username, mother, the two columns here,
or, if I was using the users
table, having to specify idnum,
username, password, fullname,
I can just say SELECT *.
Give me everything in that row.
And if I SELECT * from moms
where username equals jerry,
I am given this set of information back.
So here's the thing that's
cool about databases,
though-- we don't have
to just have two tables.
And in particular, we
don't have to have just one
table that stores every relevant
piece of information about a user.
If we wanted to store, in addition
to what we have there, information
like their address and their date of
birth and their social security number
or whatever else we
wanted to keep about them,
this table could get bigger and
bigger and bigger and bigger
to the point where it becomes
almost annoying to have to use it.
But we can use relationships
between different tables.
And that's where the
term relational comes
into play for a relational database.
We can set up our tables
within our databases
carefully enough that we can
use relationships between them
to pull information from where we need
it without all that information having
to be located in the same
table in the first place.
So, for example, here is our database
as we last left it, with three rows
in each of the users
and the moms tables.
Now let's imagine a
hypothetical situation
where we want to pair a user's full
name, which is currently only stored
in the users table, with
their mother's name, which
is only stored in the mother table.
They're not on the same table right now.
So we can't use the same sort of
select query that we used before.
We have to use what's
called a select join query.
It looks pretty similar to
the select query before.
But we're adding one extra
piece of information, which
is what tables we're joining together.
So I want to select a specific
set of columns from one table,
joining another table
onto it just temporarily.
It doesn't really merge them.
But it creates this sort of
hypothetical table that does merge them.
On predicate, where
predicate is-- basically,
we're trying to find where
the two tables overlap
so that we can create this
merged table just temporarily
for purposes of this query, and
then have them separate again.
So, for example, I might have
a query that looks like this--
SELECT users.fullname, comma,
moms.mother FROM users joining the moms
table onto it temporarily ON--
which is akin to WHERE--
users.username equals moms.username.
And this syntax is also a
little unfamiliar, right?
I'm now prepending some of my
column names with table names.
The reason I'm doing this is
particularly because of the last line
there, where in each of those two
tables I had a column called username.
I need to disambiguate between them.
So I need to specify what
table and what column.
That's all that's happening here, is I'm
being very explicit about which column
I want by specifying not only the
column name, but also the table name.
So here is what would happen if
I executed this select query.
Here are our two tables at the outset.
This is all of the information that
I'm trying to get to start with.
I'm going to join these two tables
together where where users.username
equals moms.username.
Newman does not appear in both tables.
So I'm not going to even come close to
extracting that piece of information.
Kramer does not appear in both
tables, so that one's out too.
But jerry and gcostanza
both appear in both tables.
And so that is sort
of the overlap point.
And you can think about
this as if we have
our users table, which is
like one circle over here,
and our moms table, which
is one circle over here.
When we're joining, it's sort
of like if it's a Venn diagram.
We're trying to figure out what
those two tables have in common
and using that as, like, our
anchor point for the join tables.
So that's what we did here.
We found where the two
tables have data in common.
And based on that, we create
this hypothetical table
called users & moms that contains
all of the information that
appears in both of those tables.
But notice that the second column
there sort of indicates the overlap.
This column refers to data that is in
both users.username and moms.username.
So that's what we're extracting here.
But remember that this query,
we didn't want everything.
It wasn't SELECT * FROM users JOIN
moms WHERE users.username equals
moms.username.
Username We just want the full
name and the mother's name.
And so that's what we extract.
And so that really
long query just results
in us getting this set of information--
users.fullname and moms.mother
for every row in both tables where
the username happens to be the same.
All right.
So that was a bit more complicated.
You probably won't do too many joins.
Fortunately, the last two
operations are a little bit easier.
So update is the third of
the four major operations.
This is what we use to modify
information in the table
or change it or update information.
The skeleton looks like this--
UPDATE table SET column equals value--
so we're updating some column to have
a new piece of data in it--
WHERE predicates.
We're trying to figure out
which row we want to update,
and then we're updating that column.
So, for example, I want to
UPDATE users SET password equals
yadayada WHERE idnum equals 10.
You can probably guess
what's going to happen here.
We're going to find the
row whose ID number is 10,
and we're going update the password
there from "fusilli" to "yadayada."
Pretty straightforward.
And the fourth and final
operation that we do in SQL
most commonly is to delete, which
strikes or completely removes
information from a table.
The basic framework looks
something like this--
DELETE from some table
WHERE predicate, or, again,
where some condition is satisfied.
So, for example, you might want to
DELETE from our users table WHERE
the user name equals 'newman.'
Now, if we did that, and this
was our table to start with,
you can probably guess
what's going to happen.
After that query executes, the
row whose username is newman
is no longer in our table.
Now, all of the operations
that we just showed
are really easy to do in the
graphical interface of phpMyAdmin,
which, again, comes with
most implementations of SQL
that you might download.
Here's the catch, though--
phpMyAdmin, despite being
very user-friendly to use,
requires manual intervention.
You're going to have to log
in and click on some buttons
to delete information or
update it or change it.
And we don't want to do that.
We're a webmaster, right?
We want things to happen
automatically for us.
We want programs that we write
to make those changes for us.
So we don't want to go into
phpMyAdmin and make those changes.
We have to write code
that does it for us.
Fortunately, SQL
integrates really nicely
with a lot of modern programming
languages such as Python or PHP
that have functions that you can
use to connect to your database.
And then the programming
language has other functions
that will query the database
for you and make those changes.
Now, we're going to leave off for now
exactly how those languages do that.
We'll save that for a video
on those languages themselves.
But know that that is
something that you can
do to avoid having to do any
sort of manual intervention
when you want to update or do any sort
of operation at all on your databases.
My name is Doug Lloyd.
This is CS50.